Frederic Rodrigo Gruger collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Frederic Rodrigo Gruger collection
1911-1935
MS 1454
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of original sketches and drawings by Frederic Rodrigo Gruger illustrating stories written by prominent American authors and published in several major journals and magazines. There are twelve mounted and numbered pictures containing illustrations for "Stover at Yale" by Owen Johnson, which was serialized in McClure's Magazine in 1911 and 1912. There is an unnumbered, mounted picture containing an advertisement for "Stover at Yale," and a photograph of author Owen Johnson and Frederic Rodrigo Gruger at the latter's home in Bermuda. There are also several illustrations by Gruger for poems and stories that ran in other publications between 1919 and 1935.
Gruger, Frederic Rodrigo
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederic R. Gruger, Jr., 1986.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Frederic Rodrigo Gruger was born on August 2, 1871 in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. He attended the American Academy of Art in Philadelphia, and worked as an illustrator from the 1890s to the 1950s. He died in New York City on March 21, 1953.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of original sketches and drawings by Frederic Rodrigo Gruger illustrating stories written by prominent American authors and published in several major journals and magazines. There are twelve mounted and numbered pictures containing illustrations for "Stover at Yale" by Owen Johnson, which was serialized in McClure's Magazine in 1911 and 1912. There is an unnumbered, mounted picture containing an advertisement for "Stover at Yale," and a photograph of author Owen Johnson and Frederic Rodrigo Gruger at the latter's home in Bermuda. There are also several illustrations by Gruger for poems and stories that ran in other publications between 1919 and 1935.
McClure's magazine; Stover at Yale; Magazine illustration -- United States; Art, American; Illustrators -- United States; Drawings; Gruger, Frederic Rodrigo; Johnson, Owen, 1878-1952; Yale University -- Students -- Fiction
- Original accession
  - "Stover at Yale" [illustrations from McClure's Magazine mounted and numbered], 1911-1912 (Box 1)
    - Print 1/12, October 1911 (Box 1)
      - What's Your Name and General Style of Beauty?" [p.586] (Box 1)
    - "All Square to the Wind" [p. 590] (Box 1)
    - Print 2/12, November 1911 (Box 1)
      - "McCarthy and Dopey McNab Were Solicitously Occupied in Applying Lather to his Bare Feet" [p. 17] (Box 1)
    - Print 3/12, November 1911 (Box 1)
      - "They Had Given Regan the Beer Shampoo" [p. 19] (Box 1)
    - Print 4/12, November/December 1911 (Box 1)
      - "A Second and Third Time He Flung Himself Heedlessly at the Swinging Figure" [p. 22] (Box 1)
      - "How Do You Feel? Said McNab Taking His Pulse Professionally" [p. 209] (Box 1)
    - Print 5/12, January 1912 (Box 1)
      - "Boning Out of the Greek, Said Stover" (Box 1)
    - Print 6/12, January 1912 (Box 1)
      - "Stover Went to the Window; They're Running Around Pierson Hall Like a Lot of Ants, He Said" [p.306] (Box 1)
    - Print 7/12, January 1912 (Box 1)
      - "The Period of Duns Set In and the House Became a Place of Mystery and Signals" [p. 311] (Box 1)
    - Print 8/12, January/March 1912 (Box 1)
      - Untitled illustration of a young man resting on pillows [p.303] (Box 1)
      - "Often the Dialogues that Followed Were Farcically Humorous; Only Little Wookey, Solemn as an Owl, Never Laughed" [p. 563] (Box 1)
    - Print 9/12, February/April 1912 (Box 1)
      - "Pike Scratched His Ear and Wrinkled His Long Pointed Nose in a Grimace" [p. 457] (Box 1)
      - "Hello There Brocky; Come On Up" [p. 715] (Box 1)
    - Print 10/12, March 1912 (Box 1)
      - "Stover at Yale" [p. 558] (Box 1)
    - Print 11/12, March 1912 (Box 1)
      - "I Like You in Pink, Wookey; Always Wear Them" [p. 573] (Box 1)
    - Print 12/12, April 1912 (Box 1)
      - Untitled illustration oftwo young men, one holding a pipe and the other reclined in a chair, having a discussion [p.719] (Box 1)
    - Advertisement for Stover at Yale October 1911; photograph of author Owen Johnson and Frederic R. Gruger at the latter's home in Bermuda, 1912 [mounted together] (Box 1)
  - Other illustrations, 1919-1935 (Box 1)
    - "The Beauty of Holiness" [illustration for "The Beauty of Holiness" by William Lyon Phelps; published in Good Housekeeping Magazine November 1931, p. 61 (Box 1)
    - "Elementals" [illustration for "Elementals" by Steven Vincent Benet; published in Cosmopolitan Magazine, March 1922, p.16] (Box 1)
    - I Am No Mere Knight of Wits as You May Take It. In Fact I Am Lord of the Fair Acres of Arcady [illustration for Free Air by Sinclair Lewis; published in The Saturday Evening Post, June 21, 1919, p. 22] (Box 1)
    - "The Only Kind of Security...the Opportunity to Earn a Living" [illustration for "Security" by Walter Lippmann; published in The American Illustrated Magazine, May 1935] (Box 1)
    - "Sir Willie ofthe Valley" [uncaptioned illustration for "Sir Willie ofthe Valley" by Stephen Vincent Benet; published in Harper's Bazaar, February 1923, p. 46] (Box 1)
    - "The Wisdom of Folly" [uncaptioned illustration for "The Wisdom of Folly" by William Lyon Phelps, published in Good Housekeeping Magazine, May 1930, p. 85] (Box 1)